when you think about your cardiovascular
health avoiding heart attack stroke
peripheral artery disease and the like
you normally think about risk factors
like weight blood pressure and so on but
the reality is there's also links to the
plaque on your teeth and your overall
dental health so how are heart disease
and your dental health connected how
strongly are they connected and what are
some solutions for that I roped in with
help of Dr Dave McCone d DS to clear up
some confusion and in usual physionic
style we'll dive into the mechanisms and
clinical data along the way so assuming
you're not an anti-dentite rer he's just
a dentist yeah and you're an
anti-dentite
I am not an anti- denti you're a rabbit
anti-dentite let's listen in on my
Illuminating conversation with Dr McCone
we're going to jump straight into some
of the clinical data like looking at
this study where researchers took data
collected over 15 years and look for a
link between stroke a cardiovascular
disease outcome and varying levels of
dental disease known as periodontal
disease now across around 177,000
participants the researchers Quantified
the amount of Strokes suffered by people
diagnosed with periodontal disease and
those who were deemed to have good
dental health and then compared the data
to determine if there was an increased
risk if we look at those data we can see
the different types of periodontal
disease along with the severities on the
left side GI score there stands for
gingivitis and the horizontal axis is
the increased risk relative to the
healthy group at the very top now if the
squares move to the right that indicates
increased stroke risk clearly across all
conditions stroke risk is elevated now
it's always possible this is associative
data that people with worse periodontal
disease also just consume more food or
more sugary food that makes them more
likely to be obese for example or some
other Factor fortunately the data that
we just reviewed accounted for a list of
factors which includes obvious
confounding factors but we needn't rely
on this evidence Dave brought my
attention to some more corroborating
information these studies where there's
there's even these control trials where
they will take people who have
cardiovascular disease or they'll take
people who have paral disease and they
will Implement appropriate treatment
like St roof plane and then they will
look and see did they actually decrease
inflammatory markers was there a reduced
risk of cvasc disease I think more and
more we are seeing that there is a
causal link um obviously nobody would
say this is like a primary treatment for
heart disease but it is something that
is very important um and again even even
to the sense that we see some of the
plaque and we see predominantly in the
mouth you know we'll we'll see in
arteries where there's plaque build up
you know certain type of plaque but
we'll still see that bacteria in these
other locations so I I think these days
we are seeing that there is more of a
causal there okay two important things
there one the clinical trials showing
reduced systemic inflammation from
Dental improvements alone and then Dave
mentioned that bacteria from the mouth
have been found in Our arteries the
second one as fantastic IAL as it sounds
is something that we'll address later
Let's uh tackle the clinical data first
Dr McCone Dave is spot-on there's a
metaanalysis putting together several
randomized control trials on different
Dental interventions to improve oral
health and the researchers indicate
reductions in inflammatory molecules
like Incan 6 but surprisingly also blood
pressure was reduced so how cool is that
since both inflammation and blood
pressure are heavily implicated in
cardiovascular disease this offers some
more direct evidence that improving
Dental Health can have a profound effect
we'll be covering more on this at the
end okay great but how exactly does our
Dental Health affect our heart and our
blood vessels let's turn to Dave Anu as
he describes why bacteria coat our gums
and the consequences that milu leads to
inflammation so uh you know I'm sure
people who are listening and are
following your channel I've heard about
various inflammatory markers that you
might look at like CRP or like cyto
kindes like il6 and i1 TF Alpha things
like that and it's the same thing and
that and that is a big reason why we
think it leads to other systemic issues
but that inflammation does build up in
the oral cavity um certain bacteria make
it a more acidic environment so um
obviously there's there's billions of
bacteria in the mouth and and of
different types so um nobody would be
able to just name all of them but we
have some that are very responsible so
if we look at peridial disease looking
at like TJ jaalis one people talk about
t dtic Cola t for cyia versus like strep
mutants this one we'll talk about for
cavities so um but all in all that more
acidic environment that is created is
negative for both carries or what people
think of as cavities as well as paradon
disease and and that getting worse over
time Cor Ates with increas in levels of
inflammation so bacteria can generate an
acidic environment as well as thrive in
that acidic environment and there are
billions of them with hundreds of
different types the buildup of bacteria
can lead to the release of different
inflammatory molecules in fact if we pop
open these scientific reviews the
researchers describe how after we brush
our teeth the enamel of the tooth the
hard outer section almost immediately
begins building up with a layer of
proteins and carbohydrates called a
pelic this pelic is a bed for new
bacteria to attach and settle as the
initial bacteria attach to the pellicle
other bacteria attach to those initial
bacteria and the cycle repeats until
many layers of bacteria sit on and
around our tooth this buildup of
bacteria especially the ones that Dave
mentions are not a welcome addition and
can lead to a pro-inflammatory state
especially in an area called the
gingival sulcus where the epithelial
cells can come in in contact with the
bacteria these epithelial cells will
begin producing many of the
pro-inflammatory molecules like Incan 6
and uh can even secrete uh C-reactive
protein locally in addition this
gingival sulcus is the main mode of
movement from the mouth to the body
circulation and remember when Dave
mentioned that the bacteria found in the
arterial
this is one of the main Roots by which
this happens again confirmed in the
scientific review when bacteria are
found in the arterial plaque it does two
things well honestly probably more but
we'll mention these two bacteria
stimulate more immune cells to invade
into the plaque which speeds up the
plaque formation and destabilizes plaque
as we've covered many times on physionic
before however a second consequence is
the endothelial cells that line the
blood vessel produce more procoagulant
molecules increasing the risk of
unwanted clot formation now two more
things I'd like to highlight another
point that Dr McCone mentions in
relation to heart disease prevention
then I'd like to get into some solutions
but before we get to that since there's
so much more data to cover here I'm
going to expand on all these points in
my physionic insiders extended version
of this video if you'd be interested in
more on the topic the link to join the
physionic insid is including live
sessions with me all access to my
analyses a private podcast and more the
link is in the description box of this
video now I found this point by Dave
especially good because it's uh not
something most would really consider I
certainly didn't and maybe my ignorance
isn't really a reflection for the
average but anyway in this study we went
over earlier the researchers also
Quantified stroke risk based on
professional Dental Care visits they
wanted to compare those who engage in
irregular visits to the dentist versus
those who went routinely and they wanted
to know if going regularly might reduce
stroke risk looking at that data we can
clearly see that regular Dental Care
showed reduced risk remember before if
the squares mooved to the right it was
increased risk so now if they move to
the left relative to the comparison
condition indicating reduced Risk by a
little over 20% again this is adjusted
for all the same factors that we
discussed earlier so it's not a pure
correlation still Dave mentions an
interesting point that goes beyond just
dental care when you visit your dentist
so I think it comes down to a few things
there and again I think with all this
you put the caveat that of course
there's it's a correlation right and we
have to understand that like people who
are going to the dentist regularly in
general are people who care about their
health more and they're probably also
seen positions more regularly and all of
that um but obviously you know not to
take away from theimportance out there I
do Dental physic I think a lot of times
people view the dentist especially if
they're not somebody who goes regularly
as like oh that it's I could just brush
my teeth it's something where I could
just clean them but when we have people
coming to us obviously we're doing very
thorough exam um these days you know
we're doing a whole series of x-rays
we're often doing like a 3D scan on on
new we're doing an oral cancer screening
we're doing intra and extraoral
screenings and so there's a lot that
involves not just the cleaning of your
teeth but just we try to take at least
in many practices we try to take a
systemic approach to it and look at
overall factors we will ask about your
health history we have a whole health
history for and so there are times where
we might identify something we're going
to do a procedure and we need to take
your blood pressure ahead of time and
then when we see oh like you know you're
hypertensive and maybe this is something
to follow up there are some patients we
know who see the dentist regularly but
they don't see their physician regularly
and so we may identify something first
um so I think that is one aspect of it I
think the other aspect is just regarding
we talk about inflammation obviously
there's a lot of research that shows
that there are systemic health concerns
with increasing levels of inflammation I
talked about CRP and you know the
correlations we see with that with other
diseases and I think that those who are
coming regularly and not just I think we
you see the research people who come
regularly they are decreasing those
inflammatory markers and I think that's
a huge Factor here tying in the relation
to systemic health so the latter point
being regular visits can reduce systemic
inflammation we went over that science
briefly before but it's something that I
hope to cover in more depth in the
future however the former point about
people getting more than their Dental
Health checkup but several key
parameters of cardiovascular health
check at a dentist's office is an
important one or also that people who
care about their health more might be
coming in more frequently or may be able
to afford it more easily in this
analysis there are a few potential
explanations but when we pair it with
the intervention studies we still see an
independent effect of improved Dental
Health alone having an effect on markers
of cardiovascular disease now what can
we do to improve our cardiovascular
health via better Dental Health four
things that we'll get into also before
we do if you like Dave's discussion
style I'll link his work down below
including a podcast that he hosts on
health and fitness it's in the
description too okay to the solutions
sure so I I think it's still fine to
talk about some of the more well-known
and boring examples first and then we
can kind of go from there so while it
might seem obvious there are many many
people who are routinely having a lot of
sugary Beverages and and that's I
mentioned beverages specifically because
from a dental standpoint I actually had
patient who asking me about this saying
you know if I'm doing a lot of cycling
for example would be okay to have this
sugar I said you know maybe from a
systemic standpoint if you are doing
let's say a 10 mile race they a sugar
might not have as negative of a
consequence but from a dental standpoint
you exercising it's it's really not
negating the fact that that sugar is
coating your teeth and creating a more
acidic environment even something like
diet soda while it would from a dental
standpoint be preferred over regular
soda it's still acidic and that acidic
environment again you're going to have
more bacteria that are going to be able
to produce more acid and then lead to
carries and other concerns so so I would
rather somebody have not that they're
necessarily going to make the decision
between these two things but if somebody
had a piece of cake for example at one
time and then they brush they floss that
would be preferable over let's say suda
or iced coffee that is very sugary all
day because that constant coating is a
is a real problem and then we definitely
see patients who are quote unquote
addicted to sodas and and again at least
Sur the Decay and other concerns so less
sugar in take less acidic beverages
would probably be where I would start um
and and then from there of course
brushing we recommend brushing twice a
day some people brush more than that um
at least once a day if if you're
somebody who's just developing a habit
at least once a day but preferably twice
a day flossing at least once a day and
there's many different ways I mean there
there's water picks there's these proxy
brushes there's regular traditional
floss um at least starting something
there is going to be very beneficial and
as is the case with you know health and
fitness once you have those big pillars
taken care of I mean that really is the
majority of it you're still going to
have to go to the dentist hopefully
twice a year you're still going to have
V vacas emergency and whatnot that we
can take care of but just like as if the
average person were to eat a healthy
diet maintain a healthy body weight
exercise four or five days a week
they're going to take care of the
majority of their concerns same thing
with dentl if you're brushing twice a
day H twice a day not having a lot of
sugar substances you're going to be for
the most part taken care of big problems
unless you have an unusual genetic
predisposition we didn't get too much
into that whether it's genetics or
environment like most same is it's the
combination you know sometimes you have
a patient who says well you know my my
mother had bad teeth my grandmother had
bad teeth it's all just genetic there
like anything there's absolutely a
genetic component but truly with with
Dentistry for the most part if your
habits are pristine you're going to be
able to Main healthy mouth and and you
not Fable to keep your teeth hopefully
for the rest of your life um beyond that
if somebody's still having concerns just
because your insurance might only pay
for two times at the dentist per year
doesn't mean you couldn't go more
frequently so you can just op to go more
frequently you go every four months or
every three months we have a number of
patients who come to us every three
months um another thing that most people
don't think about or know about would be
sugar-free gum so sugar-free gum
obviously any gum is going to result in
salivation and so obviously wouldn't
want you chew in a sugary gum constantly
but a sugar-free gum would improve
salivation without that negative effect
and and actually not only not a negative
effect but xylol is something that is
what we call anti-cariogenic and so
xylol that is in the most sugar-free
gums will be anti- carogen and can help
prevent D disease unfortunately as we
know Nick the will end up killing you of
heart disease in about one or two years
after consuming it but you know at least
you'll have a nice
yeah I'm glad you slipped that
in as we're talking about cardiovascular
[Laughter]
disease yeah we'll have to uh have to
put a little like a please don't take
that people to that to that XY doll
video okay to simplify this into a few
rules one avoid continuous exposure to
sugary and acidic foods and especially
drinks if you do brush your teeth soon
after two two brush your teeth at least
once per day preferably twice and floss
every day three see your dentist on a
regular basis don't be an anti-dentite
like Jerry Seinfeld four Xylitol based
gum protects against some dental harm
this is briefly confirmed in this
analysis and on that last Point Dave
cheekily mentioned that Xylitol will
cause cardiovascular disease he's
referring to a video that I did a while
back on a study looking at Xylitol and
the link to cardiovascular disease to be
clear he was joking and in that video I
mentioned xylot gum is likely perfectly
fine in fact I'll link it for you right
here otherwise I have more on the topic
here too thanks to Dave for joining and
thanks to you for hanging out
[Music]